<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-07T14:57:39-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Remillard’s Thoughts</title><subtitle>This is a place to put my thoughts down, as well as tutorials and accomplishments, either emotionally, mentally, physically, or career wise. I hope that sharing this part of my life can help others accomplish things they wish.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Becoming A Remote Employee Within A Year</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/29/becoming-a-remote-employee-within-a-year.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Becoming A Remote Employee Within A Year" /><published>2019-05-29T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/05/29/becoming-a-remote-employee-within-a-year</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/29/becoming-a-remote-employee-within-a-year.html">&lt;p&gt;I started working at SendGrid a little over a year ago, moving from my hometown to Orange County, California. I took this opportunity because at the time I did not have any commitments or responsibilities chaining me to my hometown, making it the perfect opportunity to pick up my belongings and move to a whole new city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a fantastic experience, a sense of freedom and adulthood that comes from packing up your tiny sedan, driving out of state and into a new one, to a new city, sight unseen. Although being in the office of Orange County was a requirement for my new job, I found moving was a critical experience to building my character in every facet and was a catalyst to &lt;em&gt;feeling&lt;/em&gt; like an adult, however, I had unfinished plans in my hometown, I knew moving to a whole new region of the United States would cause tension with maintaining relationships in my hometown. Within the first week of working at SendGrid I reiterated my hopes of moving back and working remote to my boss during our first one to one meeting. I appreciated my boss, he was upfront about wanting to get us to that point where I could be remote but was skeptical that it could be done within a year. However, I persisted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working remote has always fascinated me even before the start of my career, hearing that an employee was working from home painted an image in my mind of wearing pajamas with a cup of coffee, cooking breakfast for my significant other while in a meeting and having a ton of energy to exercise after work in lieu of commute times. As I advanced in my career, the idea of working from home fascinated me grew deeper, I dug into the day in the life, reading email articles from &lt;a href=&quot;https://remotive.io/&quot;&gt;Remotive&lt;/a&gt;, and the more I learned the facts about working remote, that picture in my head quickly shattered. It is not at all what many think it may be, although, the shattered image of working from home did not shatter my desire, for my desire grew. I wanted to chase after that lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1*QhYYRTqViztTZc8Snke3mA.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Here’s an image just because ¯\_(ツ)_/¯&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of caveats for working remotely, some downsides and some upsides. However, there is something I feel like many prospective employees who wish to be remote tend to ignore this honest fact: working remotely is not for everyone. It is a matter of your work style and self-discipline, this is not to say some people may not ever have the opportunity to work from home permanently. Working remote is very much of a self-starter/self-motivation type of employment, it can be cultivated within oneself, however, trying to cultivate it while in the process of currently being a remote employee will most likely be the cause of decreased work performance. Ultimately, being a remote employee takes a great amount of continuing trust on both the employee and employer, that the quality of work is solid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After learning more about what it really is like to work remote, I wanted to begin to cultivate the discipline to be a successful and trustful employee of a company. Well before I even applied to SendGrid I started to work towards building my character in those key components, it was not an easy journey but &lt;em&gt;WHEW&lt;/em&gt;, has it been worth it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;being-a-trustworthy-student&quot;&gt;Being a trustworthy student&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I did to build my work ethic to be more aligned with a remote employee was transferring to an online education platform. Attending school physically has been a driving factor for many universities, especially regarding their location, priding themselves for emphasizing a strong hands-on teaching method. Fortunately, my field of study does not require a physical presence, regardless of what universities may believe and state, the ability for me to learn material should not be dependent on my ability to attend a classroom from a specified time as designated from the university, especially since majority of the content that is structured to learn for my field of study is based on textbooks that I could read at any time. Understandably, the physical attendance is a discipline aspect of education, to allow a student an environment to be physically present to learn the material but also allow questions to be directly asked to the professor, which is how a majority of students learn. When looking into developing characteristics that would make me a good remote employee, the very concept of being a trustworthy student came to my mind, to still be learning the material and completing assignments regardless of a physical presence. In short, I am not stating I skipped class just to prove myself a point, if anything that is contradictory to what a trustworthy student would be. The first step in becoming a trustworthy remote employee would be aligned with being a trusted student where the physical presence is not required. I moved from an on-campus university to an online university called Western Governors University. There is a steep learning curve in learning how to learn online without a teacher physically present, it took some practice but it does force you to be a self-starter, to learn material without a teacher telling you to do assignments. Not to mention the added benefit of no physical location is that tuition is drastically cheaper than a standard four-year university!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;being-a-self-starter&quot;&gt;Being a self-starter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always been someone who easily becomes intrigued in a topic and that becomes my world for some time. Some topics stick and some don’t, however, one that did stick is programming. I started to program when I was 12 years old after being introduced to it from a friend I met online. A whole world unlocked before my eyes, that what I saw on a computer is not what it actually looks like but is visualized and brought to life through hundreds of thousands lines of code. That absolutely blew me away. The more curious I become with how something on a website or in an application worked, the more motivated I was to dig into it further. This trait has been so helpful in becoming a full-time remote employee, I was able to demonstrate to my employer that butts-in-seat is not required for me to complete my tasks, that I naturally dig deeper to learn and solve a problem, all that is perceived as a trait of a self-starter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;being-persistent&quot;&gt;Being persistent&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would not be successful in becoming an on-premise to remote employee if it wasn’t for my amazing boss who constantly batted for me and supported my goal in every possible way. During my interview at SendGrid and my first week of employment, I was upfront about wanting to work remote which I believe being honest with my intentions from the start allowed a positive platform to discuss the possibility of transition from an office to remote worker. Quickly after I had conversations with my boss and the principal engineer on my team about working towards achieving that transition. I appreciated how they both wanted me to achieve my goal as well as made it their goal as well, however, they were honest in the uncertainty of reaching that within a year as an entry-level engineer. Regardless, we devised a plan to work towards readiness for working remotely and planned to take it one step at a time. Nearly every other week I would discuss with my manager my readiness for remote, we trialed various techniques to become remote ready and provide ammunition for discussion with higher-ups. Some of the things we tried in a different state, slowly working my up with the number of days I would work from home in a week to meeting our director for further discussions and process of transitioning. Overall, I could not stay as persistent as I did if it was not for my amazing and supportive team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has taken quite some time with a slow progression of proof that working from home does not decrease my productivity and quality of work, and with quite a bit of discussions with my manager and my team, I was fortunately given the opportunity to work remotely within a year of my employment. I am excited to see what this can produce in my career. My hope of this article is to advocate remote work by explaining from an employees point of view to employers and advocate amendments to their policies on allowing remote work as well as encourage employers and employees to build trust within each other.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I started working at SendGrid a little over a year ago, moving from my hometown to Orange County, California. I took this opportunity because at the time I did not have any commitments or responsibilities chaining me to my hometown, making it the perfect opportunity to pick up my belongings and move to a whole new city.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Productivity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/10/15/productivity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Productivity" /><published>2018-10-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-10-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/10/15/productivity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/10/15/productivity.html">&lt;p&gt;If you’re anything like me, there is so much in this world that you want to learn, do, or create. But frankly, we just don’t have the luxurious time to do so in our life. What we can control is implementing productivity habits with the limited time we have to efficiently spend our opportunity free time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1*03trDcoAOygoWW6eU3Kz9g.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Time is ticking…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being productive is a product of having good time management skills. Good time management is a learned habit, ironically it takes time to become efficient at with a dash of determination and perseverance, two things that can make us feel like we are wasting time. It helped me with this mindset of overcoming the feeling of wasting time by working on time management by understanding and referring to examples in my life that I took, when I had to take a step back to take two steps forward or sidestep onto a road where I can take many steps forward compared the previous road. I wanted to share a few things that helped me become more productivity and progress with hobbies or my careers exponentially, hopefully, the things I learned will benefit you the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;calendar-notifications&quot;&gt;Calendar Notifications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always figured getting notifications from my calendar would become a nuisance, I already get frustrated with all the email, text, and phone call notifications I receive, I figured adding more to that noise would be a pointless addition to my goal for better time management. Luckily, I decided I need to stop assuming and give it a shot. After all, setting up and configuring would take me an hour top, and deconstructing the calendar notifications would a total of five minutes, what is the harm? I decided a Sunday night before the work week, I set aside an hour to set up my calendar on my phone and laptop, setting time aside for everything I needed to do this week, as well as putting in reoccurring blocks such as work or appointments I had. Here is the caveat I believe that distinguished the usefulness of using a calendar with my phone rather than a physical calendar: I set up reminders. I learned after many years of running back to back with meetings, appointments, work, sports, and many other things, is always during those events I was always thinking what I had to do next, or what I had to do the next day, or how I can do it. Simply, finding that sweet spot of a reminder that helped me remember what is next and not to worry, was a trial and error. A 15-minute reminder was all I needed to know what is next, to start to prepare for that mentally and physically. The most important part of this time management activity is I set up a reoccurring event every Sunday, I would block out an hour to review and add, edit, delete calendar events for that week. Doing this requires discipline, it belongs to the idea of picking up as you go which is often referred to cleaning up the hour, which happily marries alongside with cleaning up your calendar, your weekly schedule needs grooming too! Getting a notification on my phone and my laptop was enough where I wouldn’t forget about my notification but rather I was able to use that time to prepare myself for the next event, which alleviated the stress and helped me compartmentalize my day, which leads me to my next learned lesson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;compartmentalization&quot;&gt;Compartmentalization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concept is a relatively new concept that I was introduced while having a conversation with one of my boss’ about how the meetings back to back all day with no breaks was burning me out. Although I do think everyone is aware of this method unconsciously, very rarely do any of us actively put it into practice consciously. It really helped me to put this concept into practice when I accepted that I was not good at multitasking, how I produced much better results and quality work when I focused on something 100%, rather than two tasks at 50% each. The return on investment (ROI) for compartmentalizing my time and energy seemed much higher when focused on one task rather than anything more than that. That alone was enough to convince me that this is something would help me benefit my time as I had more energy and focus for the many other things I had or wanted to do in the day. On top of this, this has helped me a lot with being more present with where I am at, honestly, this has helped me a lot of relationships. Focusing on the time now I have with them instead of what I need to be doing in an hour from then. Whatever I have to do in an hour is in an hour. Now, there is a caveat. Having too long of focus time during compartmentalization can backfire, I learned if I focused on one thing for too long it actually wears you out. Make sure you always find a healthy middle!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pomodoro-technique&quot;&gt;Pomodoro Technique&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is most likely the more well-known method for time management and maximizing productivity. However, I would delve into this deeper on the benefits and return on investment (ROI) for this, but C&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/swlh/how-to-work-40-hours-in-16-7-d9038681e652&quot;&gt;hris Winfield does an amazing job on how this works,&lt;/a&gt; describing how to work 40 hours in 16.7 hours as well as shares his personal experience of the journey to finding that healthy middle when using this technique. Rather instead of reiterating what he said, I encourage you to go read his article and give it some claps! Luckily, I come from a technical background and was able to program my own Pomodoro clock, however, there are plenty of online websites that implement this just as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1*ojHAJr6qL005Bz-kDHlrag.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;Picturing things while meditating can help you clear your mind&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;this-is-counter-intuitive-but-trustme&quot;&gt;This Is Counter-Intuitive, But Trust Me&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think one thing that many articles seem to miss about time management and productivity is actually managing the stress by taking time to yourself. If the idea of how the ROI is better when you put 100% effort and focus on something instead of multiple tasks with a fraction of your focus, then how can you maintain that level without burning out and keeping a high productivity level? Ultimately, we all need to recharge our batteries regardless of our “verted” versions of ourselves, introverted and extroverted, both sides are neither 100% of one, therefore there are times we need to relax and take time to other things. My father once told me that in life, it is good to have three things to tend too. Family, Work, and You. To this day, I do not necessarily agree I can’t have more than one “you”, I can have several hobbies and projects at the same time happily, but rather they are primarily all things that do not require time deadlines as well as I refuse to put pressure on myself to complete those projects on a strict early deadline. However, I do find the general sentiment of three things in your life a happy medium for me. It was a trial and error process to find that number, but I believe having that balance can lead to better productivity and progress in each facet of your life. Some of the things that have greatly helped me with productivity is actually setting a time in my weekly schedule where I block out two one hour times where I meditate. Meditate on my thoughts, feelings, actions, overall oneself. I do admit this was one of the most difficult actions I did to help me become better at time management and productivity, the idea of sitting and doing nothing was nothing more than grinding metal against metal, it was gritty in my mind. Once I overcame that mentality and accepted that time to myself to better myself would help my overall life happiness, balance, reflect, and progress, and again, referred to the times that meditating helped me succeed in those areas, it became an event that I looked forward too. An hour of silence can be the most blissful time of your week, helping you move forward past those barriers in your heart and mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ending&quot;&gt;Ending&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many different techniques and habits you can build that are more narrowed down to what works for you. Everyone is different, what works for me works for me, but you can use these techniques as a framework to do trial and error for what works for you. Frequent reflection and analyzing how things are going for the different planes of your life while learning time management and productivity tips are part of the process of becoming more efficient. No one wakes up one morning after a night of attempting to become more productive, is automatically extremely productivity consistently. Remember that this should be a marathon, not a race. Burning yourself out is the exact opposite of what you want, in fact, that could set you back further then where you would be if you try to be productive at all. However, the feeling of being productive and seeing your progress is worth the attempts at becoming a marathon productivist.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">If you’re anything like me, there is so much in this world that you want to learn, do, or create. But frankly, we just don’t have the luxurious time to do so in our life. What we can control is implementing productivity habits with the limited time we have to efficiently spend our opportunity free time.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">4 Things To Consider For Backups</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/10/14/4-things-to-consider-for-backups.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4 Things To Consider For Backups" /><published>2018-10-14T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-10-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/10/14/4-things-to-consider-for-backups</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/10/14/4-things-to-consider-for-backups.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1*QOsU_Tk9SbPqfT0OpzKH7w.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We store everything we need on these things&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since becoming a DBA, I have learned that something as simple as a backup can actually come with a lot of caveats that may not have simple solutions. In my mind beforehand and have worked at other tech places, backing up data was a simple backup to a cloud storage or a SAN drive of some sort. You back it up once a day or once a week, that is it. If something happened such as file went missing or someone lost their computer, we can just roll back with what we got on file. However, since becoming a DBA, there are many different hurdles I never thought of or considered, especially when it comes to a high availability environment with high SLA’s. Here are 4 things to consider when creating your backup system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-availability&quot;&gt;1. Availability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first point encompasses different aspects when it comes to availability, however, there are three primary points I want to hit on when it comes to this topic. The first aspect to think about is how accessible are your backups. If the only backups you keep are an off-site cold storage, that will be a bottleneck if there ever is a case where backups are required to bring a service online. This is typically well known not to only have off-site backups and not practiced often, but I have seen cases where that is the only way to obtain certain files and documents. Another aspect is the latency of the backup server. If the backup server is one that is on the backlog, neglected, with the oldest and outdated switch, this will cause issues of unavailability of the backup, as well as a lengthy disaster recovery process taking hours to access. Lastly, the question to ask yourself is how long would it take you from the point of learning that you will have to recover the backup, to actually getting it implemented and accessed by the service. This is in consideration of both points listed above but may also consider the method of accessing the backup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-datarecovery&quot;&gt;2. Data Recovery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This point is not talking about bottlenecks or recommendations for disaster recovery, but rather a thought exercise of the availability of data for a disaster or a recovery process. Something to think about when creating a backup system is the frequency of the backups being created and the critical data that is being generated or collected from the point of a data loss and the latest backup. Say, backups are created at midnight every day, but sometime afterward data is corrupted, therefore any work done for that day is gone. How do you prevent that from happening? Understandably, there is little you can do to prevent several minutes of data corruption, there may be times where that is the best a company can do. However, this is something to think about, how to prevent data corruption from ruining an entire day worth of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-hardware-and-softwarefailures&quot;&gt;3. Hardware and software failures&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple answer to preventing hardware and software failures is making backups upon backups, on several different servers in several different regions of the world. However, these still happen and can still erase important data. Any part of the entire stack can fail: the backup software or script, the backup server, the archive server hard drives, network connections, a bad commit or bad query, server overload, even drive space which can fill up overnight. Layout the most critical parts of the backup systems’ stack, and implement tools to monitor and self-correct when issues arise. Always maintain off-site external backups, and create policies for data retention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-scalability&quot;&gt;4. Scalability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, as the company and software grow, so will databases and backup sizes. With this comes a reiterated set of problems, especially with where on the stack is the system going to be overloaded, and where is expansion going to alleviate the most. Best practices to scale your scalability to implement good third-party monitoring software for just about any part of the stack, network with our database administrators with how they solved problems, and stress test your backup system to see where faults pop up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ending&quot;&gt;Ending&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, these points to look for were helpful and gave you some food for thought. Just remember, databases are some of the most complicated parts of the services and software, DBA’s handle a lot more than perceived.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We store everything we need on these things Since becoming a DBA, I have learned that something as simple as a backup can actually come with a lot of caveats that may not have simple solutions. In my mind beforehand and have worked at other tech places, backing up data was a simple backup to a cloud storage or a SAN drive of some sort. You back it up once a day or once a week, that is it. If something happened such as file went missing or someone lost their computer, we can just roll back with what we got on file. However, since becoming a DBA, there are many different hurdles I never thought of or considered, especially when it comes to a high availability environment with high SLA’s. Here are 4 things to consider when creating your backup system.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Top MySQL Queries for New Database Administrators</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/30/top-mysql-queries-for-new-database-administrators.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Top MySQL Queries for New Database Administrators" /><published>2018-09-30T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-09-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/09/30/top-mysql-queries-for-new-database-administrators</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/30/top-mysql-queries-for-new-database-administrators.html">&lt;p&gt;Before entering the field of database administration, I wanted to look up what common queries they used to help solve any issues. Upon searching, I found some basic commands that the database administrator’s (DBA) used, although, my personal experience has been slightly different. I found that DBA’s don’t really use a handful of queries to solve issues, but rather various scripts and software to help debug problems. However, to start off with some groundwork, I found that these 3 MySQL queries helped me start to understand what and why these various scripts and software did what they did. Also, note that I typically learn best when pushed into the firehose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-explain-how-to-optimizing-queries&quot;&gt;1. Explain How To Optimizing Queries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EXPLAIN query is often used with Data Manipulation Language (DML) queries to help you optimize queries, to simply put, make them run faster and better. Although this query can be a bit to understand at first, it was one of the few queries that were never mentioned in most commonly top result articles on MySQL queries. I wanted newer DBA’s to find this, and look into it, to help them better their databases. To help understand this query, you can look into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/8.0/en/using-explain.html&quot;&gt;MySQL documentation&lt;/a&gt;, and supplement it with various chapters from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Joe-Celkos-SQL-Smarties-Fourth/dp/0123820227&quot;&gt;Joe Celko’s book&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-getting-the-number-of-rows-in-atable&quot;&gt;2. Getting The Number of Rows in a Table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never thought how often this query would be run, but surprisingly it is a lot more than expected. I have seen software developers and other DBA’s do this command similarly, and although which one is correct is trivial as they are essentially the same, one way could help you transition better into a different but same SQL database. The query to count the number of rows in a table follows the syntax of SELECT COUNT(1) FROM table whereas the query I am talking about is SELECT COUNT(*) FROM table&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in this &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/1221559/count-vs-count1-sql-server&quot;&gt;StackOverflow post&lt;/a&gt;, there is no difference between COUNT(1) and COUNT(&lt;em&gt;) , however, in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/What-are-the-most-useful-MySQL-queries&quot;&gt;AskTOM post&lt;/a&gt; from Oracle, they are stating there is a difference for Oracle DB’s, stating that COUNT(1) is a non-optimized version of COUNT(&lt;/em&gt;) . So far, that seems like it’s pretty much it. To do one or the other seems unimportant, but what is important is how to get the number of rows. This query could be used to compare between a replica and snapshotted replica, to ensure that data has been transferred. Please note that this is NOT a surefire way to check, but can be a little extra for natural nature of paranoia as DBA’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-show-me-what-the-table-looks-like-incode&quot;&gt;3. Show Me What the Table Looks Like in Code&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to the previous two other queries, this might be the simplest but often overlooked when new DBA’s start. This query has helped me immensely with familiarizing myself with unknown tables, and to get a better idea of what is happening and how to improve it. DESCRIBE table or DESC table shows the layout of the table structure in code, you can see what is the foreign key, primary key, what data types are used, and so on. You do have to select a database beforehand, but this can help you with understanding your environment furthermore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;there-is-much-more-to-learn-there-always-willbe&quot;&gt;There is Much More to Learn, There Always Will Be&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To many, these queries may be simple and second nature, but to me and hopefully many other new DBA’s, this content is helpful. This is not even hitting the tip of the iceberg as a DBA, there is so much to learn and there always will be, but hopefully, this gets you started.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Before entering the field of database administration, I wanted to look up what common queries they used to help solve any issues. Upon searching, I found some basic commands that the database administrator’s (DBA) used, although, my personal experience has been slightly different. I found that DBA’s don’t really use a handful of queries to solve issues, but rather various scripts and software to help debug problems. However, to start off with some groundwork, I found that these 3 MySQL queries helped me start to understand what and why these various scripts and software did what they did. Also, note that I typically learn best when pushed into the firehose.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Recovering Data From A Failing Hard Drive</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/28/recovering-data-from-a-failing-hard-drive.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recovering Data From A Failing Hard Drive" /><published>2018-09-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-09-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/09/28/recovering-data-from-a-failing-hard-drive</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/28/recovering-data-from-a-failing-hard-drive.html">&lt;p&gt;While attending school a couple years ago, I had a friend come up to me in a frenzy, claiming his computer won’t turn on the day before finals containing all his homework as well as programs he wrote for Computer Science class. The laptop he handed me was a thick 2010 MacBook Pro that brought back nostalgia of carrying the dumbbell weight in my backpack to and from school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I attempted to boot it up, I noticed that it would struggle to boot into the OS, and if it did, it has horrible lag and eventually shutdown. I was able to deduce this to a corrupted OS, as he mentioned he has not updated it in a while. I did a repair on the disk from the disk repair utility upon bootup, and noticed the hard drive was formatted incorrectly. This made me start to question the years of IT experience I had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safe mode was not working, I could not reinstall the OS, repairing the disk did not work, I could not boot into the system, nor could I format a hard drive with the OS and boot into that. All I was left with is single user mode, which fortunately I was able to get root through an exploit at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;/sbin/fsck -y&lt;br /&gt;
/sbin/mount -wu / # Mounts the volume of root directory with r/wOnce I logged in, I would try to move files onto a USB I plugged in, occasionally the computer would crap itself, which led me to believe that the computers hard drive is failing, and I knew I had to make it quick as how much time I had was unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;I checked the SMART status of my drive:diskutil info disk0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;grep -i smart&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The output was exactly what I was expecting, failing. I plugged in the USB external hard drive and searched for it by doing ls /dev/disk*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily it popped up after a few ls commands as /dev/disk1s2. So the next step is to create a directory in volume, than mount it and copy files over to that directory, than eject it, the hard drive should than contain the files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;mkdir /Volumes/hdd&lt;br /&gt;
mount_hfs /dev/disk1s2/ /Volumes/hddLuckily I had no errors at this point. After getting with my friend to discuss where and what files he wanted to keep, I did a multiple cp -R commands, and copied the files over to the directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then ejected it, and luckily the files moved out without any issues. Boom!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">While attending school a couple years ago, I had a friend come up to me in a frenzy, claiming his computer won’t turn on the day before finals containing all his homework as well as programs he wrote for Computer Science class. The laptop he handed me was a thick 2010 MacBook Pro that brought back nostalgia of carrying the dumbbell weight in my backpack to and from school.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">3 Tips To Keep Your Home Network Secure</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/technology/security/2018/09/06/3-tips-to-keep-your-home-network-secure.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="3 Tips To Keep Your Home Network Secure" /><published>2018-09-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-09-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/technology/security/2018/09/06/3-tips-to-keep-your-home-network-secure</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/technology/security/2018/09/06/3-tips-to-keep-your-home-network-secure.html">&lt;p&gt;As technology around us becomes more advanced and connected to the internet, there becomes more of a reach of vulnerability with our day to day lives. While going to friends and family houses, I have noticed that regular consumer or day-to-day people are hardly aware of how easy it is for hackers to own their network. So to spread awareness, here are three tips to help keep your home network secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-set-a-router-password&quot;&gt;1. Set a router password&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people are not aware that you can access your routers machine by entering it’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IP_address&quot;&gt;Internet Protocol (IP)&lt;/a&gt; Address when connected to your WiFi. You can find the router or modems IP address by opening up Command Prompt for Windows and typing in the following code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ipconfig
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scroll down using the scroll bar, and look for a set of numbers by ‘Default Gateway’, that will look something along the lines of 10.0.0.1 or 192.168.1.1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;If you are on an Apple machine, you open Terminal and type in netstat -rn&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;grep default to figure out what the router IP address is. Or, you can open up System Preferences &amp;gt; Network &amp;gt; Click ‘Advanced’ &amp;gt; Click ‘TCP/IP’. From there, there will be a row that says router, followed by the IP address.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you copy and paste that address into your web browser, it should pop up with a login pop up, or a login page. If you have not set your router or modems password, the username should be admin, and the password would be password. In some cases, there is not a username, and in some cases, there will no username and password. If you want to be sure, you can visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://192-168-1-1ip.mobi/default-router-passwords-list/&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; to see what your factory default password is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are able to get in, look around and set the router password to something secure that is easy to remember, but difficult to guess. You can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lastpass.com/password-generator&quot;&gt;LastPass password generator&lt;/a&gt; to generate a secure but easy to read passwords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-ensure-your-wifi-is-set-to-wpawpa2&quot;&gt;2. Ensure your WiFi is set to WPA/WPA2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default most routers when initially are set, set the WiFi encryption to WPS or WEP. Those encryptions can be pretty easily cracked, which can lead to consequences of intruders breaking into your network, and an ability to spy on your network activity. But rather, the fix is to change that to WPS to WPA/WPA2 or just WPA2. This makes it near impossible for people to break into your network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can make this change on your computer, but it would be best to do this through your router or modem. Showing how to do this can be difficult because every router varies in terms of where this is, but the general idea of where you want to look for is, first, log onto your router. Then look for the menu and go to Wireless &amp;gt; Click ‘Security Mode’ and select WPA/WPA2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-frequently-update-router-firmware&quot;&gt;3. Frequently Update Router Firmware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The router you have has essentially its own operating system. Just like software or your computer needs to be updated, so does yours. This can help apply any new security patches or bug fixes. You can update the firmware from the webpage on your router and mode, access via it’s IP.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology" /><category term="network" /><category term="security" /><summary type="html">As technology around us becomes more advanced and connected to the internet, there becomes more of a reach of vulnerability with our day to day lives. While going to friends and family houses, I have noticed that regular consumer or day-to-day people are hardly aware of how easy it is for hackers to own their network. So to spread awareness, here are three tips to help keep your home network secure.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breaking Into The Technology Field</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/technology/rant/2016/06/23/breaking-into-the-technology-field.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking Into The Technology Field" /><published>2016-06-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-06-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/technology/rant/2016/06/23/breaking-into-the-technology-field</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/technology/rant/2016/06/23/breaking-into-the-technology-field.html">&lt;p&gt;A quick introduction: I started programming at the young age of 12 when I became fascinated with code after my friend showed me how websites were made. Since then, I have created a wide range of websites; a social network, text based games, command line interface, administrative and analytical tools, shells, and an intrusion detection software. My love and curiosity for programming has continued to grow ever since I landed an internship in software development and then as a field service technician. Now I am currently a part time IT Assistant for a local company, which I manage and set up the company’s web servers, phone system, work and network stations, and provide web development, in parallel with attending a local university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a college student attending a local university in one of the biggest tech hub cities, it’s horribly competitive to get any internships or part time tech jobs, it’s to the point that it seems like all it takes is knowing the right person or starting your own company. I believe I can speak on behalf of the people in a similar situation, that it sucks. It sucks when entry level jobs require you to have a B.S. in C.S. along with 3–5 years of experience, making it nearly impossible for us young ones to get into this field. Although this is not an article to complain, I do believe that part of this is the cause of business’ not wanting to take a risk on young engineers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a current college student attending a local university in one of the biggest tech hub cities, it’s horribly competitive to get any internships or part time tech jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understandably, it seems smarter from a business and financial standpoint to not take a risk on a young engineer, when you can get yourself an experienced engineer with decades of experience. But frankly, that supply of senior engineers will slowly diminish the longer you do not take a risk on fresh graduates or students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all honesty, there is plenty of entry level engineering jobs that do not require experience, it’s just somewhere else. I do live in a tech hub, where Amazon, Microsoft, and several other big companies have started, thus flooding the city with people that migrated to get a job, and thus the demand is more, and there is a limited amount of positions. It’s simply supply and demand issue. Thus increases the competition as there is more applicants than is jobs, obviously why it has become more difficult to get into the tech field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, a message to incoming graduating students, make yourselves unique. Build a portfolio while in college, and the chances of you getting a job will be significantly higher. Do not be discouraged, do not be afraid to move to get the experience either.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="rant" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html">A quick introduction: I started programming at the young age of 12 when I became fascinated with code after my friend showed me how websites were made. Since then, I have created a wide range of websites; a social network, text based games, command line interface, administrative and analytical tools, shells, and an intrusion detection software. My love and curiosity for programming has continued to grow ever since I landed an internship in software development and then as a field service technician. Now I am currently a part time IT Assistant for a local company, which I manage and set up the company’s web servers, phone system, work and network stations, and provide web development, in parallel with attending a local university.</summary></entry></feed>